Mss.B.W41 Mss.B.W41
American Philosophical Society
George Weedon military correspondence, 1777-1786
Mss.B.W41
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
156 items.
George Weedon (1734-1793) was Captain in the French and Indian War and a General in the American Revolutionary War. Between the two conflicts he was a prominent citizen of Fredericksburg, Virginia, operating a tavern in that city which served as a meeting place for George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, Patrick Henry, John Marshall and others to discuss politics and the future course of the American colonies.
Weedon, George,1734-1793.
Box 1
Scope and Contents note
These letters are with officers of the American army and others, including Horatio Gates, Nathaniel Green, Thomas Jefferson, Marquis de Lafayette, Richard Henry Lee, J.P.G. Muhlenberg, Thomas Nelson, Baron von Steuben, and George Washington.
General note
This correspondence is indexed in "Calendar of the Correspondence Relating to the American Revolution, of Brigadier-General George Weedon" (Philadelphia, 1900).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Hugh Mercer, 1835; accessioned, 1913 (1913 50541).
Biographical/Historical note
George Weedon (1734-1793) was Captain in the French and Indian War and a General in the American Revolutionary War. Between the two conflicts he was a prominent citizen of Fredericksburg, Virginia, operating a tavern in that city which served as a meeting place for George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, Patrick Henry, John Marshall and others to discuss politics and the future course of the American colonies.
Weedon was born in 1734, a few months after his father’s death, in Westmoreland County in Virginia. His widowed mother married William Strother when Weedon was still very young, and the family moved to Stafford County, Virginia. Weedon’s first military experience came with the onset of the French and Indian War. He served as a Captain in the Virginia Militia, having been commissioned an officer after recruiting other soldiers.
After the war Weedon married Catherin Gordon and settled in Fredericksburg. Catherine’s father, John Gordon, operated a tavern in the city, and when he died Catherine’s mother continued to run it under as Mrs. Gordon’s Tavern. After Weedon’s marriage to Catherin, he took over operations of the tavern, under the name Weedon’s Tavern. The tavern served as post office for Fredericksburg and the surrounding area. As proprietor, Weedon became a prominent citizen of the city. He kept a stable with pure-bred horses for the amusement of visiting gentlemen, was an ardent sportsman and became secretary of the Jockey Club.
The tavern also became a meeting place for future leaders of the American Revolution, including Washington, Jefferson, Marshall, Patrick Henry, and many others. Weedon, by all accounts, was sympathetic to the cause of revolution from an early stage, and when the war started, he abandoned the tavern to join the army. Weedon has a distinguished military career during the war, and commanded the Virginia Militia at Gloucester Point during the Siege of Yorktown. He was present at the surrender of Lord Cornwallis in 1781. The Peace Ball, which was held in Fredericksburg to celebrate the victory at Yorktown, was held at Weedon’s Tavern and was attended by a large number of people, including Washing and Lafayette.
After the war Weedon served as Mayor of Fredericksburg, 1785-1786, and as the first President of the Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia. Weedon eventually retired to his country estate outside of town.
George Weedon died two days before Christmas in 1793.
Early American History Note
The George Weedon military correspondence contains a wealth of information on the American Revolution and its immediate aftermath. There are letters from the Morristown and Valley Forge winters, although the bulk of the material comes from 1780-1781. The collection follows Weedon’s service throughout the war. His correspondence often details movements, strategies, supplies, and life in the Continental Army. Weedon also receives letters from correspondents stationed throughout the United States. This correspondence can provide information on events happening in these other locations. Correspondents include Baron von Steuben, Thomas Jefferson, Nathaniel Greene, Peter Muhlenberg, George Washington, Marquis de Lafayette, Horatio Gates, and many others. Washington, in particular, is a frequent correspondent who writes to Weedon seeking advice on military action.
Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806; Green, Nathaniel, 1710-1758; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794; Muhlenberg, John Peter Gabriel, 1746-1807; Nelson, Thomas, 1738-1789; Steuben, Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, Baron von, 1730-1794; United States. -- Army -- Records and correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799; American Revolution; Colonial Politics; General Correspondence; Military History; Military history, Modern -- 18th century.; Military Records; Political Correspondence
- Papers
  - Letter to [George Weedon], July 28, 1780; 12x7-1/2; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Scope and Contents note
    Richmond, L.S. 1p. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.32.) Printed: Boyd, v.3, 514.
  - Letter to [George] Weedon, Oct. 22, 1780; 7-1/2x6; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Richmond, L.S. 1p. (see Military Correspondence of...Weedon, no. 43.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 61.
  - Letter to [J. P. G. Muhlenberg], Oct. 28, 1780; 12-1/2x8; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Richmond, L.S. 1p.and end. Enc.wanting. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 48.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 78-79.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], Nov. 2, 1780; 12-1/2x8; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 1p.and end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 24.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 91.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], Nov. 3, 1780; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Richmond, L.S. 1p. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 52.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 94.
  - Letter to [Thomas] Jefferson, Nov. 3, 1780; 10-1/2x8-1/2; Weedon, George, 1734-1793
    Richmond, A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 28.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 97.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], Nov. 6, 1780; 12-1/2x8; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 2p. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 55.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 97.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], Nov. 7, 1780; 6-1/2x7-1/2; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 1p.and end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.56.) Printed: Boyd, v.4, 100.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], March 31, 1781; 14x8; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 1p. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.64.) Printed: Boyd, v.5, 308-309.
  - Wetter to [Thomas] Jefferson, April 2, 1781; 12-1/2x8; Weedon, George, 1734-1793
    Williamsburg, A.L.S. 1p.and end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 69.) Printed: Boyd, v.5, 324.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], April 3, 1781; 9x7; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 2p. and end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.72.) Printed: Boyd, v.5, 337.
  - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson], April 3, 1781; 13x8; Weedon, George, 1734-1793
    Williamsburg, A.L.S. 2p. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 70.) Printed: Boyd, v.5,338.
  - Letter to [George Weedon], April 4, 1781; 14-1/2x9-1/2; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Enclosure wanting. (see Military correspondence of ....Weedon, no. 73.) Printed: Boyd, v.5, 351-353.
  - Letter to [George] W[eedon], April 23, 1781; 9x7-1/2; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Richmond, L.S. 1p.and add. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no. 85.) Printed: Boyd, v.5, 545-546.
  - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson], April 25, 1781; 9-1/2x7; Weedon, George, 1734-1793
    A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.87.) Printed: Boyd, v.5,555-556.
  - Letter to [George] Weeden [sic]., Undated; 4x6; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Military correspondence of...Weedon, no.30.) Concerning the war.